Okay.
You all right?
Yeah.
You'd think these trips would get easier,
but it's just the opposite.
Well, I feel the same way, Ange.
I know this is what we do.
This is our life.
But it just seems like the world
is moving so fast...
...and right now
things are changing so much.
They sure are.
I'll tell you something.
It's not gonna be easy for our kids.
They're going into a different world
than the one you and I came into.
Yeah.
You know,
both our kids are doing great.
But it worries me when Danny
doesn't take school seriously.
Him missing class.
That could come out...
It might hurt him when he's out
looking for a job, you know?
The competition out there.
When I was starting out...
...you could make captain if you put
your head down and did your work.
But young guys coming up now...
Companies want things faster
and cheaper.
And 50 guys compete for every job.
Everything's different,
and big wheels are turning.
You gotta be strong
to survive out there.
I hear what you're saying.
It's gonna be okay, right?
Oh, yeah.
Gonna be okay.
This is a special
security announcement.
Please maintain control
of your personal belongings at all times.
Unattended baggage is subject
to search, inspection and removal.
- I love you.
- Love you too.
- Have a safe trip.
- I'll call you from there.
They're here!
Hurry, Muse!
What the hell are you doing?
Why aren't you out on the water?
You know what you're supposed to do!
You should be out there
earning money!
But we caught a ship last week.
That was last week!
The boss wants money today!
Bring Garaad another ship soon...
...or you will answer for it!
Everybody, get back to work now!
Stay out of my way today.
Hufan!
I'm going to get us something big!
Those who want to make money,
come.
Muse, take me with you.
Does your sister know you're here?
She's selling khat up there.
This is her best stuff.
When we get a big ship,
you will be well paid.
You want to work?
Do you know how to steer a boat?
Go, go.
I'm ready.
- What do you have for me?
- Money.
- When are you gonna give it to me?
- As soon as we're paid.
Spread out!
Let my other man choose his crew.
Next time bring me something
if you want to work.
Come on, Bilal.
Hey, Skinny, I can steer your boat.
If you choose me, you won't regret it.
Okay, Elmi.
I need somebody strong.
Somebody like this?
I want him.
Get out of my way!
Why did he pick him?
He's from another village.
Move!
Faster, move faster!
See if you can get more power.
Okay.
You!
Get over here!
Come help us!
Okay, pull it in!
Sign right there, sir.
You have a good day.
- Hello, Cap. Let me get that for you.
- Morning.
Attention, all crew. All crew.
1500 departure three out.
- Hey, good to see you, Cap.
- Shane. Good to see you.
- Good to see you.
- Hey. Carry on.
- Hey, bos?
- Yeah?
Get on that safety rail, huh?
- Kenny.
- Yeah?
I want you to go down to the deck office,
grab Jimmy, get on the Lodestar.
That ballast, move it five points.
- Take care of that now.
- You got it.
How's the family, Cap?
Oh, you know.
Andrea's a champ, one kid gone,
another kid going.
How are the boxes?
Oh, you know.
Just putting a few last containers on.
Twenty-four hundred tons of
commercial cargo, 200 tons of food aid...
...166 tons of freshwater,
250 metric tons of fuel bunkered.
Walk me through the plan.
So here we are in Salalah.
Travel down the coalition corridor
to Djibouti.
Then we exit the shipping lane
south of Socotra.
Socotra, okay.
Then we're on our own down the coast
through the Somali Basin...
...all the way down to Mombasa.
We need five minutes
on that reefer bow.
We should be able
to unload the containers around 0800.
Well, let's tighten up security.
We are going
around the Horn of Africa, right?
We got pirate cages. They were all open.
All the doors are unlocked.
I want everything closed, locked,
even in port.
- Right.
- Fine. Ready to leave. 1500.
Absolutely, Cap. You got it.
Stow the gangway.
Last lines in.
Okay. Lower it.
Sixteen-B ready. Take it up.
Tighten it up.
Hey, slow down.
Bow clear.
Stern lines are clear.
Bow thruster full starboard.
Bow thruster on.
All lines clear. Ship is under way.
- Dead slow ahead.
Keep those hatches locked down.
- Cap.
- Morning.
Check that rigging.
- Shane.
- Yeah?
We need those time sheets.
She's winking at me.
But it turns out that's what they do.
I'll show you this place. I'll take you.
I'll have two beers
and a bucketful of sin, please.
Yeah. About done with that coffee?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, we're done.
That's 15, guys.
Back to work. Come on, let's go.
- Jesus.
- See you down there, Mike.
Their main route is packed
with ships...
...but we can't attack a herd.
This one is alone.
Morning.
Hey, Cap.
- Cap.
- Morning, Cap.
Shane, I want to do some security drills,
unannounced.
Starting now.
What? Fire, man overboard?
Everything.
Ken, you're the duty officer?
- Yeah, Cap.
- Right.
Boat with two armed men is approaching
on your starboard beam.
- No, no. Whistle first.
- Let's go.
That way the pirates know we're aware
of them and are ready to defend the ship.
Hustle up. Let's go.
Attention, all crew.
All crew.
All men to your stations on deck.
Repeat,
all men to your deck stations now.
Let's do this.
Come on... Get those keys off your hip.
Put them in your pocket. Come on, guys.
Pirates capture you
and find those keys...
...they'll have access to every door
on this ship.
Get those hoses on.
Bring it around, bring around,
bring around.
- Watch it, man.
- Ready with number six.
All right.
You tied up?
All done here, Shane.
- Hey, Cap, this is Shane. Do you read?
- Yeah, Shane, go ahead.
Things are looking good down here.
We're getting close with the hoses.
All right. Let me know
when you're ready down there.
Copy that.
Shane, come up to the bridge.
Okay.
What's up, Cap? Everything okay?
I don't like the look of that.
- Yeah, Cap.
- Chief, I want all your guys on station.
Still in the drill?
This is real-world. Someone coming up
on our starboard quarter.
Got it.
Port, 5 degrees.
Let's see if they follow us.
Port, 5.
Get the crew back
to their muster stations.
Right.
Attention, all crew.
Return to your muster stations.
Repeat, return to your muster stations.
This is not a drill.
This is a real-world situation.
- Yeah, Cap.
- I want to come up to 122.
Second mate and helmsman
to the bridge.
You're good. Bring her on up.
Now get me U.S. Maritime Emergency.
Two skiffs.
Can't tell how many they're carrying.
Copy that.
There's no answer
at the U.S. Maritime Emergency line.
- Raise the UKMTO.
- Right.
What's up?
We got two skiffs approaching.
Get on the radar.
Yeah, this is the Maersk Alabama.
Here's the captain.
UKMTO.
- Operations?
- Receiving.
This is the Maersk Alabama.
Our position is 2 degrees 2 north
by 49 degrees 19 east.
Our course is 180.
Our speed is 17 knots.
We have two skiffs approaching
at a distance of 1.5 miles...
...with a possible mothership following.
- Potential piracy situation.
- Copy, Alabama.
Alert your crew,
get your fire hoses ready...
...and follow lockdown procedures.
Yeah. Is that it?
I'm relaying your transmission now,
but chances are it's just fishermen.
They're not here to fish.
She's really big! Get ready!
You worry about yourself, skinny rat!
Both skiffs carrying armed men.
- Distance?
- One and a quarter miles and closing.
- Yeah, Cap.
- I wanna bring it up to 125.
- You're still good.
- One twenty-five.
Brothers,
we're going to make a lot of money!
Slow down! The waves are too big!
They're at one mile now, Cap.
Only one mile.
Coalition Warship 237,
this is Maersk Alabama.
Maersk Alabama.
Go, Alabama.
Our position is 2 degrees 2 north
by 49 degrees 19 east.
Our course is 180.
Our speed is 18.5 knots.
We are being approached
by two pirate skiffs...
...with a possible mothership following.
We require immediate assistance.
We have a crew of 20.
We are preparing our weapons now
but request air support if possible.
Copy?
Copy, Alabama.
Be aware, a gunship is in the air.
ETA your position, five minutes.
Five minutes. Thank you, 237.
Did you hear that? Did you hear that?
We've got to get out of here!
Turn back, turn back!
What are you doing?
Where are you going?
Come on! Keep going!
Yeah, we got one down.
But the other one's still coming.
Half a mile out.
We need to make a bigger wake.
- Yeah.
- Cancel the limits. One two nine.
Yeah, you're on the edge
with Cylinder Number 5.
Do it.
- Port, 5 degrees.
Faster, faster!
They're at a quarter mile now.
- Starboard, 5 degrees.
Hurry, hurry! Go!
We're pushing this engine too hard!
Faster, faster!
Come on, let's go!
This thing is busted.
- Then fix it!
- I'm trying!
They're not messing around.
Lit us up from miles away.
Must've been tracking us.
Why doesn't the company
give us armed guards?
Move it in. The captain's here.
Blips on the radar that are clocking
at 27 knots.
They were moving.
We cannot outrun these guys.
Obviously, we all just went
through a dangerous situation.
Two skiffs, both with armed intruders.
Now, we all know that's a hazard
in these waters, but you performed well.
The ship performed well.
The authorities
have been made aware...
...so I think we have the situation
well in hand.
From now on,
we just follow our normal duties.
Mate, what do you got?
Yeah. We're all on double shifts
until we make it through these waters.
All right. Chief, can you keep
your engineers on roster?
We'll keep a guy in the ECR
around the clock.
All right. Enjoy your coffee.
Cap.
They're coming back.
Amen. Yeah, that's right.
If they come back, we'll follow procedure.
They worked today, they'll work again.
We got the speed, we got the height,
we got hoses that can sink those skiffs.
We will follow the procedures even if
we have to shut down, lock down...
...go dead in the water
and wait for help.
Now, wait. I'm a u...
Okay, I'm a union guy, okay?
Twenty-five years, all right?
I'm telling you now that they're
not paying me enough to fight pirates.
You all signed up for a route
around the Horn of Africa.
- What did you expect?
- I didn't sign up for the Navy over here.
- You signed up for the route.
- For a cargo ship.
- What did you expect?
- Not getting attacked without weapons.
Why don't we get out of here?
Put room between us.
- Go where?
- In eight hours...
...we could be a hundred miles from here.
- Hundred to a 150.
There's five pirate bands
in this part of the world.
You go out 300 miles, you run into one,
go 6, you run into another.
Our job is to move the cargo
as fast as possible. That's the job.
If anybody doesn't like it,
if anybody wants off...
...if anybody doesn't like this route
between Salalah, Djibouti and Mombasa...
...come to my office
and sign the paperwork per the union...
...and you'll be on the first flight home
out of Mombasa.
Enjoy your coffee.
Let's get back to work.
Go get those guys squared away,
will you?
The ocean was rough. Really rough.
Hufan, I'm telling you,
our boat couldn't take it.
Nothing was working for us.
Hurry up.
We need a bigger one for that ship.
I want this welded by the morning...
...by tomorrow, got it?
Elmi.
When will that engine be ready?
We've gotta fix it.
This thing is old and weak.
It's a piece of shit.
Shut up and fix it
for your crew of women.
Why don't you give me your engine?
Shut up, Skinny. You talk too much.
I may be skinny, but I'm not a coward.
What did you say?
Say it again!
You think you're somebody?
The coward is the first one in the grave.
Captain, this is Shane.
Yeah, go ahead.
I think you better get up here.
Coming.
- Where are they?
- Port quarter.
One-point-seven miles, captain.
Guy's coming on his own.
Sound the alarm.
Get U.S. Maritime Emergency for me.
Muster stations. This is not a drill.
Everyone to muster stations.
- This is not a drill.
- Come on.
Shit.
Come on. Let's go. Go.
- Yeah, Cap.
- They're coming back.
I want max revs. Take the limits off.
Copy that. Canceling all limits.
- Five degrees starboard.
- Starboard, 5 degrees.
Get ready.
U.S. Maritime Emergency line.
This is the Maersk Alabama.
We are under pirate attack at a...
- What's happening?
- Ken, get out here.
- I need eyes on the wing. Skiff coming in.
- I'm on it.
Our course is 166.
Our speed is 19 knots.
Copy that, Alabama.
Relaying to military channels now.
Copy that.
They're coming in fast, Cap.
Alabama.
Alabama ship.
Somali coast guard.
This is a routine check.
Stop your ship now.
We are coming aboard.
We're here to help you.
- Shane, they're dead astern.
- Jesus Christ.
- Yeah, Cap.
- We're gonna need the hoses.
Yeah, your pumps are good.
- Count it down for me, Shane.
- Yeah. They're at 800 yards.
- Prepare for hard turns.
- Stop now!
- Standing by.
- Alabama, this is your final warning.
Stop the ship.
They're not stopping.
Show them who we are, Muse.
Shoot at them!
Shots fired! Shots fired! Hit the hoses.
Turn!
Coming in close, Cap.
Shane! Hose seven has slipped.
Bay 17. I'm on it. Shit.
- Be careful.
- I'm on Channel 3.
It's clear over there!
They're coming back in.
Untie the ladder.
Give me the other one.
Shoot him!
Let's go, let's go!
Hurry up, Bilal.
Move your ass, kid.
Channel 3. Shane, get out of there.
Get everybody
down to the engine room.
I need you in command there.
Stop him!
All crew! All crew!
All crew to the engine room!
All crew to the engine room now!
Come on, let's go. Move it.
Come on, men.
Higher. Get it higher.
- Port, 30 degrees.
Hook it on!
They got the ladder up.
Starboard, 30 degrees.
Get out of my way.
- Port, 30 degrees.
- Starboard, 30 degrees.
- Starboard, 30.
Someone's shooting at us.
Hang on.
Just get together against the wall.
- Cronan. Cronan.
- Yeah.
Hold them by the door.
We'll get a head count.
Go down to the door.
- Mike?
- Yeah.
- How long till you can shut her down?
- Five minutes.
Four pirates onboard.
Four pirates,
coming towards us down the main deck.
- Lock down the bridge.
- Yeah.
Listen up. We have been boarded
by four armed pirates.
You know the drill.
We stay hidden no matter what.
I don't want any hostages.
We stay locked down until help arrives.
No one comes out until you hear
the nonduress password, "suppertime."
Jesus.
If the pirates find you, remember,
you know the ship.
They don't.
Make them feel like they're in charge...
...but keep them away from the generator
and the engine controls.
Stick together...
...and we'll be all right.
Good luck.
Take everybody to the bottom
of the engine room.
Hide them behind the cylinders.
Try to split them
into groups of threes and fours.
- Hey! Don't move! Don't move!
- Okay, okay.
- Don't move, I said! Don't move!
- All right. All right.
Okay.
Okay. All right. Okay.
Don't move! We have four!
- All right, all right.
- Don't move! We have four! Four!
No, no.
Get away. Get over there.
Captain.
Relax. Nobody get hurt.
No al Qaeda here.
Just business. We want money.
When we get paid,
everything gonna be okay.
The ship.
Where from?
The ship? America.
It's an American ship.
America? Yes! Yes!
You?
Yankee?
Me? Yeah, yeah. Yeah, yeah.
Yankee-Irish. Yeah.
From now on
this one is called Irish, okay?
Irish. Irish.
Okay, Irish. What else you carrying?
What do you mean?
TV? Car?
TV and car...? No, no.
We just got the food...
Dollars?
We do. Kenny?
Kenny, what do we have in the safe?
We got like, what, $30,000 in the safe?
Yeah, we got like... We have...
In the safe, we got $30,000.
It's yours.
Thirty thousand dollars?
What am I? Do I look like a beggar?
What's that?
It's all right.
Hey, calm down! Calm down.
Get back there.
Yeah, yeah, over here.
We got a problem.
We pushed the ship too hard.
We're off the grid.
That means
the computer's now off-line.
- Captain. Captain.
- The ship's broken.
No one get hurt
if you don't play no game.
It's... The ship's broken. We had to go...
Nobody gets hurt. Easy.
Hey!
- Look at me.
- Sure.
I'm the captain now.
Watch this ugly one.
What are you doing?
I'm going to fix it.
Do you know how?
Hold the gun on him.
I've got him, don't worry.
Don't mess with anything
you don't know.
Come on, man.
- What are you doing?
- Just take care of that guy.
Stop the games.
Where is the crew?
I don't know. I don't know.
I'm here with you.
- Where is your crew?
- I don't know. Here, I'll call them up.
I'll get them up here, all right?
This is the captain speaking.
The pirates demand all crew members
to the bridge. All...
Every crew...
...one minute, I will kill someone.
One minute.
Another minute, I kill somebody.
I kill all your friends. One minute.
I will no call again.
Get that one
and put him against the wall.
- I'm trying...
- You think we playing?
- No, I'm doing the best...
- No play. No play.
- I'm doing the best I can.
- Easy, I kill you. Easy.
No, no. Look. You don't have to do that.
- Come on.
- You play? You play?
Take it easy, take it easy. No, no, no.
- No, look, look.
- Stop play!
Don't shoot him. Don't shoot him.
You're gonna shoot somebody, shoot me.
- Where is the crew, Irish?
- Forty seconds!
I don't know. I'm here with you.
No. Where is the crew?
I see nobody.
- I'm the captain. I'm the captain.
- Thirty second!
If you're gonna shoot somebody,
you shoot me.
- You killing him.
- It's my ship.
- Listen to me.
- You killing him.
I'm the captain.
I'm the captain, not them.
- Twenty second!
- This is between us.
I'm trying to straighten this out. Are you?
This is how you solve your problems?
You said you just wanted money.
You said this was just business.
Is this business?
- Is this how you do business?
- Ten seconds.
Die right now.
Wait.
I want to search the ship.
You wanna search the ship?
I want to search every lock and hold
of the ship now.
- You wanna search the ship?
- Now.
All right. We'll search the ship.
We'll start on the nav deck
and work our way down.
We better hope
the emergency power stays on.
We won't be able to see if it goes off.
I'll take you. We'll search the ship.
But you stop threatening my men.
- No game.
Let's go.
All right? All right, good.
Take his radio.
All right. Okay.
Go.
Gotta get these lights off.
They're gonna see us.
We need to shut down the generator
on the main deck.
- You think you can get up there?
- Yeah.
I'm gonna go to the mess, get water.
Get everyone on the lower level.
All right. I'm on 2.
Just start at the very top.
This is E deck.
And we'll just work our way down
one by one, huh?
Cargo hold is probably where they are.
There's a lot of places to hide.
And I'm not trying to trick you.
I wanna find these guys
just as much as you do.
Take his flashlight.
We should just move on,
because we're wasting time here.
Like I say,
the cargo deck's the best place to look.
Somebody messing with ship.
Engine room.
If we're going about this systematically,
we started at the top...
...we're working our way down,
so we should try the cargo deck.
Problem from engine room.
We go there now.
All right. Engine room.
It's gonna be really hot down there.
Without the power on,
there's no ventilation, no air.
Maybe we should get some water
from the mess down on A deck?
- Then engine room. Go.
- Okay.
This is A deck.
So here we are.
This is the galley.
This is where we make the food.
All right. Here, some water.
Check this room.
Oh, you wanna see in here?
This is cold storage.
It's a vegetable room.
Careful in here in the bare feet.
You could cut them
on almost anything.
Want some of this melon?
It's left over from breakfast.
It's just gonna go bad.
It's just gonna spoil.
It's usually left out
for the first meal of the day.
Maybe we should...
Go ahead, help yourself. Here you go.
Help yourself.
It's usually for breakfast, but...
Enough. Engine room.
All right.
- Cronan. Cronan. Do you read?
- Yeah, I got you.
They're on their way to you.
One is barefoot.
Is there glass you can break,
leave on the floor by the door?
I'll do it. Come on, let's go. Come on.
Here's the engine room.
Oh, my God.
Look out. There's broken glass.
Be careful.
- Put your hand up. Up your hands. Up.
- Okay, all right.
Up.
- There's a first-aid kit...
- Put your hands up!
- Who did this?
- Nobody. It was just a dumb accident.
We should get that looked at.
There's a kit in the control room.
Quiet, Irish. You think I am stupid?
I know what's going on.
We're going to search this whole room.
All of it. Now go.
Go.
I heard something!
Check the other side.
There's no one here.
Please, let's go back.
Go. Right down to the bottom. Now.
They're coming. Get ready.
Keep going. Move.
Wait. Stop here.
What? What'd you do?
- We just...
- Look at me, Irish. Look at me.
What's wrong with your ship?
- I don't know.
- Was that you?
- I don't know what went wrong.
- No.
You'll never find this crew,
not without any power on the ship.
You'll never find them.
We'll never find them.
Irish...
...I will find.
Not with him.
Look. He's gonna bleed to death.
Look, man, get us out of here.
You got a man injured.
Let's take care of his foot...
...take the money out of the safe
and call it a day. All right?
You're bad luck, Irish.
Hey, take him upstairs.
I can't move.
Take him upstairs
and tell Najee to come.
- You go with him.
- We're gonna go?
Go!
Hey.
Wait.
You're not gonna find anybody.
Don't talk. Go.
Your friend make fool of us?
Make us run around?
If one of them moves,
send them to their graves.
Here.
Hey.
We got a problem.
Your buddy's hurt real bad.
We better get this dressed.
We got a sick bay here onboard,
and this guy knows what to do.
What happened to you?
They put glass down for me.
They got me.
Where is Muse?
In the engine room.
He wants Najee to come down.
Bridge. Bridge, come in.
Alabama bridge, come in.
Do you read?
This is the crew of the Maersk Alabama.
We have your captain.
Put your hand over his mouth.
- Hey.
- No.
We have your leader.
We have your captain and his weapon.
We wanna trade.
Captain for captain. We want a deal.
Take that off of his head.
Cronan, take that off his head now.
I no kill.
Talk. Talk to your friends
so they know it's you.
Talk to your friends.
Come on, asshole. Say something.
I love America.
Hey! Get me out of here!
Listen to what these guys have to say.
What happened?
They cut my hand, bad.
We'll straighten everything out later.
Just get me out of here.
Give Irish the radio.
I'll give it to him now.
Talk.
Captain, you know,
if you wanna get off this ship...
...you don't have a skiff anymore,
but you could get into our lifeboat.